this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC Radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software digitalocean is the easiest
cloud platform to deploy manage and
scale applications of any size removing
infrastructure friction and providing
predictability so developers and their
teams can deploy faster and focus on
building software the customers love
with thousands of in-depth tutorials and
an active community we provide the
support you need digitalocean stands out
of the crowd due to its simplicity and
high performance with no billing
surprises try digitalocean for free by
getting a 100 dollar infrastructure
credit at doco /se radio hello this is
Adam Gordon bell for software
engineering radio today I'm speaking
with Orson ball author of writing an
interpreter and go as well as its sequel
writing a compiler and go Thurston lives
near Frankfurt Germany and he loves to
deep dive into programming topics like
programming languages interpreters
compilers systems programming and
databases Thurston
welcome to software engineering radio
hey thanks for having me so today I want
to talk to you about interpreters and
now you might build an interpreter so I
thought a good place to start is what is
an interpreter oh that's a good question
the easiest answer is probably that
interpreter is a computer program that
makes a computer understand the language
it didn't know before it takes input in
a specific language let's say JavaScript
and translates it to something that the
computer already understands either by
interpreting it or internally
translating it or doing something else
but the basic idea is it takes in
something and translates it while
reading in something into something that
the computer understands so how how does
an interpreter differ from a
the lines are blurry to be honest like
the the more advanced or more
industrial-grade an interpreter or a
compilers the more they you know get
similar to each other but the general
idea is that an interpreter takes the
input a programming language and
interprets it meaning it does exactly
what the input language tells us to do
for example print hello world while
reading the input write a compiler on
the other hand translates the input
language into another language which can
then later be fed to the computer to be
executed so it's a difference in when
the code that you give your interpreter
or the compiler will be executed and the
the easiest analogy that I always use is
that interpreting and compiling can be
you know seen as talking in a foreign
language to friend where you have
another friend that understand or
translates for you right so let's say
you have a friend that only speaks
Spanish but you don't speak Spanish but
your friend speaks English and Spanish
so you talk to your friend in English
and interpreting would mean that he
listens to you for sentence and then
traits translates your English into
Spanish compiling would mean that he
listens to all of what you have to say
in English and then writes down the
Spanish translation and hands it to your
second friend which only understands
Spanish does that make sense yeah that's
a great metaphor so like if I am Ruby
code and you're the Ruby interpreter so
what you do is you're translating it
from Ruby which I know to to whatever
the yeah either machine code or yeah
yeah exactly
so the computer understands only machine
code right so that means in order for us
to be able to talk to the computer in
another language we have to write
something in machine code that takes in
this other language and you know
interprets translates it for the
computer so the computer understands it
and you know you start with machine code
but then you can you know bootstrap
yourself up and then you end up with for
example Ruby
which is an interpreter that is written
in C like the most commonly used Ruby
implementation is written in C which the
computer understands because somebody
wrote a C compiler before right the
computer doesn't understand C so
somebody wrote a C compiler initially in
machine code mm-hmm that takes in C code
and outputs machine code so now you can
you know write C code and the computer
can understand which means execute it
and once you have two C compiler you can
write a ruby interpreter that is written
in C that takes in Ruby code and outputs
C or interprets it on the fly and thus
exactly what the Ruby code instructed to
so Ruby is an interpreted language and C
is a compiled language right like like
what about Python so when I run a Python
script it makes like a PI C file yeah I
think it executes that so weird where
does that fit that's that's what that's
exactly where the lines get blurry
uh-huh so this is also the case with
with Ruby except that you don't see it
because it doesn't exposed you know the
cached result of its work but when you
see a PI C file that means that the
Python interpreter takes in Python code
and it translates it to another language
and that language is called bytecode
right and this bytecode is it's you know
it's bytes but it's another language
that the Python interpreter understands
it's a more tensor language like it
doesn't have all the fluff and you know
the bells and whistles basically it's a
stripped down version of the Python code
that you put in and what the Python
interpreter does is it takes a Python
code translates it to bytecode and then
it caches this result by writing the PI
C file and you know then it executes
what's in the pie - C file so the next
time you run your python code the
interpreter can say okay this is the
same thing that i just translated to
bytecode and it's in the PI C file so I
can use this and you know directly
execute the bytecode I don't have to go
through the Python to bytecode stage
again and it's interesting because it it
when you describe it that way it sounds
a lot like the JVM yeah which is you
know so the JVM is considered a compiled
language right it produces this bytecode
but then
in fact the the JVM is interpreting this
bytecode right so in some ways yeah
what's the JVM is it compiled it
compiled or interpreted yeah the JVM is
the java virtual machine and a virtual
machine is a piece of software that acts
like a computer and that means it the
computer is a machine right and a
virtual machine is a machine written and
software and that means it emulates what
a machine does and what a machine does
in this sense is it reads in code
machine code and execute it it's when
you when you get down to it it's really
simple all the computer really does and
I'm doing air quotes here right modern
computer really does is it reads in code
and it starts executing every
instruction in this code like add one
air to print whatever right and then
when it says jump or go there or go
there it executes this but it's it's
pretty stupid but it just does this
really good this one thing like
executing code and a virtual machine
does exactly this it reads in code
instructions that are kind of close to
machine code but depending on what you
want to do they slightly different we
can go into this in detail but what it
does is it reads in the code and it
executes sit and the java virtual
machine is such a you know virtual
machine that executes Java bytecode or
JVM bytecode I guess nowadays it's you
know Gnostic it doesn't have really
anything to do with Java except of
course that it's specialized for Java
and stuff like this but what happens
when you run java code is that your java
compiler takes in your java code and it
outputs JVM bytecode
mm-hmm and this bytecode you then feed
into the JVM and this JVM it is itself
written in is it written in C++ I guess
I think it is there's a couple
implementations but I say are all c++
yeah I guess so the JVM itself is
written in a nother language right it's
which a computer I understand and it's a
piece of software that takes in Java
bytecode and just executes it's like
really in this stupid way take the first
instruction execute it take the second
instruction execute it and so on and so
forth and the reason why you want to do
this is
because despite code M it allows you to
basically strip down your Java code into
a really dense format and once you have
this format you can start to optimize it
right and you can start removing bits
that you don't need which you can only
see at this level of representation
basically and you can tune to JVM to
only do this thing like executing
bytecode really really well and yeah
that's basically the idea behind the JVM
so it's like Java is a compiled language
but the JVM is kind of interpreting the
bytecode yeah exactly
that the and it gets even blurry that
this because you you compile Java you
compile it to JVM bytecode and then the
JVM interprets this bytecode mhm right
so you have a compiler but then you have
an interpreter but here's the thing the
JVM is so optimized that violet
interprets the bytecode it's sometimes
and I'm not sure exactly when it kicks
in but it sometimes takes in the
bytecode and in the background
translates it to machine code it doesn't
interpret it but it translates it to
machine code and once it has this result
of this compilation of this translation
the next time it executes it's the same
piece of code it doesn't interpret the
bytecode but instead executes the
machine code so while it's running while
it's interpreting it's at the same time
compiling and this is called
just-in-time compilation because it's
not you know it's opposed to ahead of
time compilation which is what we
usually think of when we think of
compilation that you compile a piece of
code ahead of time that means before you
want to run it and then you execute it
later on right yeah but the JVM it
compiles it while it's running and then
executes sit immediately after compiling
and that that's that's you know like we
have like a compiler in there we have an
interpreter in there then we have a
compiler in the interpreter and then
basically the computer again acts as an
interpreter of this generated machine
code so it is blurry right so it's like
the line between compilers interpreters
it's almost like a spectrum rather than
yeah two baskets yeah I mean of course
this is you know general
these two categories of how you can
execute code by either interpreting it
which means you know reading in stuff
and then doing the stuff or by
translating it into another form so
there's these two ideas of you know how
to execute code basically these two
categories of what you can do but in in
you know production implementations of
programming languages these two get
mixed all the time for the four specific
purpose to get the best performance and
stuff like this and this is way too gets
blurry from my outsider perspective
having not you know built an interpreter
it seems to me that like most
interpreted languages are like
dynamically typed and most compiled ones
are are like statically typed but is
that is that have something to do with
implementation or is it unrelated it is
it is related and that is you know it
often has to do with like how much time
you have basically so let's say you're
compiling a program ahead of time for
example a C program right you compile it
to binary and then later on like ten
minutes later of 10 days or 10 months or
years whatever you execute it if you're
not you know stressed for time because
you want to execute it immediately
then you can do all sorts of things you
can do optimizations that means you're
compiling the code and while translating
it you go over the translated code again
and again and you'll remove you know the
unneeded stuff the stuff that's useless
for example let's say if you write code
that you know you define like three
variables or stuff like this but you
only use two in a loop and you always
increment the third in the loop but
without using the result a compiler
translates this code then goes over the
code again and again and it detects that
you actually don't need the third
variable so it throws it out of the code
right that's an optimization yeah like
that code elimination it's called now
doing this like going through the code
and and analyzing it and throwing stuff
out or maybe moving it around or
shortening it or lengthening it whatever
you want to do this takes time right
yeah and if you if you have an
interpreter and you get a programming
you you you go most of the time is right
executing it as fast as possible
like you want to put your stuff in like
Ruby right you don't want Ruby to wait
two seconds before it starts executing
your code you want Ruby to immediately
start running your code and adding
optimizations this takes time right and
so if you have a compiler you are free
to add some bit of time right of course
you don't want to take it you know you
you don't want your compilation step to
take really long time so there's a
trade-off mmm but in the general sense
with the compiler you have more time to
analyze stuff and with an interpreter
two focuses largely on executing as fast
as possible there's a trade-off between
compile time and optimizations right
yeah the more ya time you have a
compilation the more you can look for
but like an interpreter has zero
compilation time so it can do zero
optimizations exactly that's yeah that's
that's the rough idea and if you look at
different programming language
implementations of programming languages
you can see that they all make different
trade-offs in this regard for example go
they're famous for not doing a lot of
compiler optimizations there are certain
optimizations that the compiler could do
but the authors of go said no it adds
too much to the compilation time we want
our compiler to be really fast we can't
do a lot of optimizations and stuff like
this and even now where you have the
debates about adding generics to go and
go 2.0 or something the idea of 2.0
there's always this idea that hey if we
add generics how much does this add to
our compilation time and there's other
languages they just don't care about
compilation time because the result is
highly performant code right it's a
different trade-off you have to make so
in your book you use go to write to
build an interpreter for a language that
you've created right so why why did you
choose to use go in hindsight I could
say for all these different reasons but
the actual reason back then was that I
really enjoyed using go but now you know
I enjoyed using go I used it for a lot
of projects that I did at the time
for CLI stuff and for some systems
programming and I also didn't want to
use Ruby because I feel like that Ruby
kind of glossed over things like go
doesn't offer a lot of the you know
niceties of you know Python or Ruby for
example it's a pretty bare-bones
language and I wanted to really get down
to the bare bones level and you know not
have any magic not have any hidden stuff
no secrets no surprises I want to get
down to the real thing I that didn't you
see because I didn't want to worry about
memory management basically but that
being said these were my original
reasons but nowadays when I look back at
my choice of using go I'm really happy
that I went with go because it turns out
that go is extremely readable even for
programs that have never programmed and
go before I get emails you know a lot of
times from from readers who went through
the books and they implemented their own
interpreter while reading the book but
not in go
they actually choose their own favorite
language like Haskell or rust or C sharp
or whatever and this is amazing like I'm
pretty sure that if I had written the
interpreter or the compiler in Ruby in
the code and written idiomatic Ruby code
that it wouldn't be so easy to
understand and translate for non Ruby
programmers as this go code is and also
like besides the readability aspect
there's another good reason Foucault's
which is that it comes with a lot of
stuff like we don't use a lot of stuff
in the in the book to be honest like
there are no third-party libraries we
only use the standard library and not a
lot of the standard library actually but
it comes with its own testing framework
right and it comes with you know you can
easily compile the code with the
building tooling you can run the tests
with the building tooling you have go
format which is this tool that format
you go code to the one true standard so
it's not that you know it does it's not
a situation that people read through my
go code Nagar
how does he form and like why does he
have to come us here why doesn't he have
to press a stare like it's standardized
like it looks like every other piece of
code out there no
has to worry about formatting stuff it's
really easy and nowadays a lot of other
languages have this but looking back
it's like yes this was makes total sense
especially if you're writing a book for
other people to read to have a
standardized style of of coding
basically yeah it makes so I found what
you're describing to be true like in
some ways go is like a lowest common
denominator it doesn't have a lot of
fancy stuff yeah right yeah what I did
actually write a version of your
interpreter and I was using Scala which
is kind of my go-to language mm-hm and I
found it to be a lot more concise but I
think that it would be hard to follow if
you didn't know the language because
it's using a bunch of like idioms or
something ya know the same with Ruby
right you know yeah yeah but you said
it's much more concise and I would bet
that if I wrote the same code in Ruby it
would be a third of the size like that
that's my bad and I bet I also bet that
I can get even lower because in Ruby you
know you can write a really dense
program but then it wouldn't be readable
right yeah yeah and even if you even if
you do not go you know this down this
this road of code golfing where you make
it as dense as possible or short as
possible even if you do not set out to
do this then the Ruby code would still
be much denser and it would still
contain maybe more stuff that readers
need to understand and it would be
harder to understand for non Ruby
programmers and I guess the same is true
for Scala or a scheme or Lisp or Haskell
yeah go is like in some ways like it
seems to me it's like Java like it's
it's somewhat verbose but but not
complicated that I mean yeah yeah it's
the same it's like pseudo code right
that yeah you can ride the stuff like a
piece of code and go and you can hand it
to somebody else and even if they have
no idea about go they can probably guess
what you're aiming at right it's the
same with Java except that it's more
stripped-down I would say yeah so you
were mentioning you know the lines of
code so how how big does this
interpreter end up being interpreter
sounds like a daunting project how much
go code does it end up being at the end
I
I actually looked this up like a week
ago but I have to be honest I I forgot
the exact number but in the in the first
book the interpreter mm-hmm it's 3,000
lines of code and that includes tests
because the whole book or both books are
written in a TDD style that means
test-driven development which means we
always write a test first that fails and
then write the implementation so if you
go through the books from start to
finish what you have is in the first
book an interpreter and the second book
a compiler and bytecode version machine
and all of it is tested so and as we
said the go code is not really dense
right it's not concise so it's 3,000
lines in the first book and I guess
another 3,000 lines in the second book
and you can subtract half of it that's
you know that's just the tests basically
so when you get really down to it it's
not a lot of code in the first book it's
really not a lot of code and I'm always
surprised I'm looking at ago how did
this get into two hundred and forty
pages right but but when you have to
explain every line of code you know that
adds a lot of pages to a bar so this
like it's impressive how small it is
in the language that you're building an
interpreter for would you say it's like
a toy language like adding numbers or is
it a realistic programming environment
the language is called monkey and I
specifically set out to not you know I
didn't want monkey to be a toy language
that you know only does I don't know I
don't know there's other toy language
like esoteric languages they can only
print up numbers and they can only print
out letters or whatever I wanted monkey
to be as real as possible that means as
close to the languages we use on a
day-to-day basis as possible and monkey
looks kind of like JavaScript that means
it has braces right
it has different keywords so it doesn't
have functions that it has FN because I
wanted it to be more concise it has LED
statements it has you know arithmetic it
has strings as data types it has raised
hashes
has recursive function calls it has
closures which is the most interesting
feature in my opinion in the book it has
of course if it has closures it has to
have that like it has first-class
functions higher-order functions
built-in functions and you can basically
communicate with the outside by printing
hello world right that's that's the end
of the like sorry this is a spoiler but
the first book ends with you know
printing hello world so sorry if I
spoiled the ending there for you but
that's the ending of the first one and
in the second one in the second book
monkey basically stays the same so it
keeps the same set of features the
language does not change and that's you
know exactly what we want because we
keep monkey the same but switch out the
implementation right which is another
interesting thing about language is that
you know you can have the same language
implement it in a totally different way
but what you put in and what you get out
is the same except that everything in
the middle is switched out yeah when I
think of I guess this goes back to our
interpreter versus compiler talk I think
of like a language either being one or
the other but so you're saying that it's
actually unrelated to that it's it can
be a separate issue the implementation
yeah yeah but with with the added
asterisks that there is some stuff that
I think you can only do with compilation
like um this is like I'm out of my dad
fear but basically if you have some
super advanced type system stuff right
and or I don't know optimizations and
stuff like this you have to go one way
or the other like it's not it's it's not
totally independent I would say but I
guess some some listener that's you know
a proper computer scientist will say no
there's the general law that maybe this
is for I don't know but it feels to me
like there's some really specialized
thing that you can either only do in one
thing or the other make sense so if I'm
going to build a interpreter like what
are the the steps in my interpreter code
roughly I would say you first have to
Lex the input that means you have to
have a lexer which takes in your source
code as
string basically so it opened the file
and written a string or bytes whatever
you want to call it at that point and it
turns it into something called tokens
and tokens are basically you know the
representations of your source code
that's easy to head so for example
instead of having I don't know the
string lead fubar equals 5 semicolon hmm
you instead get tokens that are let then
I don't know identify your fubar then
equals then integer 5 then semicolon
think of the lecture as turning your one
single string into a list of objects or
tokens or whatever you want to call it
which is much easier to handle once you
have to go about you know what comes
after this or does this come before this
and suffix when you have to analyze the
source code right you can it's every
program and it ever had to deal with
strings knows that a proper data
structure is much easier to handle than
a single string once you have to get
into the inside of the string right so
that's the dense and first part you have
a lexer that takes in source code and
turns it into tokens and then you have a
parser and the parser takes in the
tokens and it turns it into something
called an abstract syntax tree or short
ast and the ast as the name suggests is
a tree data structure that means you
know you have a parent node for example
you have child nodes and you can walk
down the tree and analyze it and what
the Parsa does is it takes the tokens
and looks at them and turns it into
different little sub trees of this ast
for example a let statement might be a
node in a tree and it has two child
nodes one is the identifier which is the
you know on the left side of the equal
sign the name of the binding that you
want to create and then you have another
child node which could be I don't know
value or expression which is what's
happening on the right side of the equal
sign right and if you put this in a tree
structure it gets super easy to work
with it's it's better
the tokens right and if you have to
interpret the code later on you are
happy that you have a tree because
suddenly you can go what is this like
it's this a let's segment okay then give
me the left part or give me the right
part or you know you can easily access
different parts of your program
basically so we start with the string
right so we have a string that is our
program right and then so the the lexer
turns it into a list of tokens yeah all
right so the string let x equals 7 gets
turn it to a list of tokens and then the
parser takes that and turns it into a
tree where it's like let at the top and
then X on one side and seven on the
other right the parser seems more
complicated than the tokenization
process so yeah it is so like I'm used
to parsing like you talked about like a
JSON document if I if I receive one you
know and then I turn it into some sort
of internal representation but the
internal representation is very similar
to the actual document itself right all
right the parsing like a programming
language seems different somehow from
that yeah yeah in that the
representation is not like it's a whole
different data structure yeah yeah
exactly but so we're honest if you it's
hard to see but if you really look at
your code and for example let's say you
have a piece of JavaScript code and you
have a for loop right and then you have
like for the keyword then you have
opening parens then you have a
initializer didn't you have your what
you call the condition and then you have
your step
basically so I equals 0 then I less than
10 and I plus plus and then you have the
closing and then you have the opening
braces right that the limit the body of
the for loop and then you have to body
that I don't know console.log I or
something and then you have closing
prices that end the bodies to follow now
think of the braces as for example an
object in JSON like they signify that
this is now one level you know nesset
deeper right and then your parens in
that come right after the for keyword
that's also one level deeper right and
you can kind of see this in your code
that you have
different you have a structure that's
repeated all the time you do intend
ation right and you have for example you
nest your code so you have functions
nested in other functions you have a
loop bodies nested in other loop bodies
which you know if you if you squint at
it you can see hey you can probably
represent this as a tree data structure
right because you have these different
elements that are repeating which means
there's a schema to it and then you can
see that yes you can it you can nest
them right you can say it this one here
has child elements like the for loop has
the child element of the for loop body
for example and it has child element of
for loop condition or for loop
initializer and it itself the for loop
tree representation can also be nested
and be the you know the body of another
for loop node or something like that
yeah Lisp and scheme actually you just
write the tree yeah exactly and if you
if you think about this is also why a
lot of tutorials and and blog posts that
explain how to write interpreter they
use a lisp or a scheme as the input
language because they do not have to
worry a lot about deposit because you're
already writing your code as a tree data
structure all you have to do is take the
parens and turn it into a real data
structure basically so it's just
cheating like like this it's just a
language where they didn't write the
parser they're like you just write the
tree for us yeah there's one famous
article Peter Norvig
and it's about how to write an Lisp
interpreter in Python and in this
article he he doesn't write a lecture or
Pazza
all he does is he takes the code as
input and splits the string on the
parens right mmm and that that gives him
enough structure because it's already a
nested reform that gives him enough
structure to work with hit D we don't
need a tokenizing
process or like a lecture that tokenized
as the input or positive turns it into a
tree because you already have the tree
you just need to make it a little bit
more accessible by splitting the string
on the parenthesis
digitalocean is the easiest cloud
platform to deploy manage and scale
applications of any size
removing infrastructure friction and
providing predictability so developers
and their teams can deploy faster and
focus on building software the customers
love digitalocean stands out from the
crowd due to its simplicity high
performance and no billing surprises
join a community of over 3.5 million
developers on digitalocean sign up with
a free $100 infrastructure credit at
doco /se radio there are tools to help
out with this so I had used this antler
in the past and it builds a parser for
you to my understanding so why why do
you hand build a parser if if tools
exist good question to be honest like
that the short version is because I was
fed up with others using tools not the
process because after reading a lot of
tutorials and again blog posts about how
to write your interpreter and they
compute the language I was fed up with
these black boxes you know the when it
said in the text and then we need to
parse it for that we can just use this
tool and then next paragraph okay we're
done we'd now get from this tool and ast
back and that was for me like really
frustrating because I thought well what
the stuff are is are too like I want to
get down to the to understanding what
this does like I don't want black boxes
I don't want any magic I want to
understand everything so it is it a good
idea to always write your own powder I
don't know but if you want to understand
how languages work and that includes for
me understanding how pauses work then
yes it's it's a good exercise time to
build your own powder right it's it's
the same for example if you want to
learn how a web server works you're not
gonna say I'm gonna use another web
server no if you're there to learn
something you're gonna implement it
yourself because that's a really great
way to learn about the stuff but yeah if
you just want to use stuff you can use
other tools that generate a positive for
you yeah in your estimation like what
what percentage of like real-world
interpreters use like some sort of tool
and what are like hand-rolled
that's a really interesting question
because the answer is funny I would say
50 percent from from what I've seen and
I'm saying it's funny because whenever
somebody posts a tutorial about how to
write a parser or says this is how you
can write your own parser in a blog post
or stuff like this then it will always
be one or two people saying you
shouldn't write your own puzzle like
just use a tool to generate your parser
nobody like this is a solved problem and
computer science for 40 years and just
use a tool and you don't have to worry
about it and I guess they're right to an
extent but then you look at the real
implementations of programming languages
for example go right and then you
realize oh they wrote their own puzzle
that's interesting why did they do that
like these are not dumb people writing
go right they're pretty smart so why did
they choose to write their own partner
and it turns out there are legitimate
reasons for this because if you use a
tool to generate a parser you end up
with generated code and as we all know
generated code is like rule of thumb not
the most beautiful code right it's
generated code like there's this good
generated code but as a rule you can say
it's not as readable as handwritten code
and then it's also not maybe as
optimized for your specific use case as
you want it to be or it contains too
much for your specific use case that you
you know you have like extra baggage
that comes from this generic tool that
doesn't really understand what exactly
you want because it's not built for your
exact use case so you can hand roll also
you know you build your own power so
that is really tailored to your specific
use case and it's easier to understand
most of the time and it's easier to
maintain because you know you only write
code you don't write code that generates
other code which is like this added
layer of indirection I would say and you
know you can you can test it more easily
outside and that's usually what I hear
why people choose to do this and there's
there's you know it's not a small number
of languages that have this I guess or
that let's take an example from the
other side mmm
the Ruby programming language does use
generated passer and it uses a tool
called yak which is I guess 30 or 40
years old like it's a parser generator
and it takes in a so called
grammar file that specifies what your
language looks like and what the parser
should recognize and what it should turn
the input into and these are you know
these these grammar files are written in
their own language so you have to know
basically this DSL in order to be able
to read and understand them now in these
grammar files you often mix this meta
language or DSL with some of the code
that you want to have generated so in
the case of Ruby you have this grammar
file that contains bits of yaks language
and bits of C code which is what the
Ruby interpreter wants to generate and
this file in in Ruby's case is it's
basically a black hole like nobody
nobody dares to go near it
nobody dares to touch it because ruby
has a really really flexible syntax and
this lie I don't know that this file is
adding a few thousand lines long and I I
don't have the exact number but it
wouldn't surprise me if it's I don't
know twenty thousand lines long or
something I guess it's a really
monstrous file and it's hard to maintain
nobody understands it maybe one or two
people understand it but not a lot more
and you know if they had built their
part of by hand you know there's no
guarantee that it would be better but
you know I would bet that it wouldn't be
this you know this monstrosity that
depends on another tool and basically
two languages that you need to learn in
order for it to understand and would
probably be you know easier to to
understand and maintain and like it
could be written yeah in C where there
is you know like techniques for for
abstract and grouping things where like
the the Yaak grammar it's not a
full-fledged language right so you don't
have the other full power yeah that's
that's I guess that's a nice point about
DSL or specialist languages in general
like what if you hit their limit like
here it's not as easy to
add another layer of abstraction or your
own abstraction as it is in a
general-purpose programming language so
at this point
okay we've taken our string turn into
tokens yeah turn that tokens into a tree
yeah and then so what are we done
no then this is where basically the
magic happens right now you have the
tree in hand which is just a
representation of the input program now
you need to interpret it and in in in
the easiest way that means you just go
over this tree like you walk down the
tree or you know you go eye to right
over it and just execute what it says
right and this is like this is really
easy to do let's say you have a data
structure that you know has different
child nodes where you can say child node
type equals print statement or something
right like you can check if this child
node is a print statement then you could
basically interpret your program by
going over the ASD and going over every
child node and checking is this chart
node and print statement and if so then
take the value that the user wants to
print and print it by using the puts
language at the put statement or the
lock statement of whatever language you
just wrote you interpreting or if it I
don't know if the ast says 1 plus 2 then
you can say oh the user wants to add 1
plus 2 oh yes we can do this this is 1
plus 2 that's 3
let's return 3 right and then you know
somewhere else in the program you take
this result of this evaluation which is
what you're doing
and you then print it I guess or put it
somewhere else or save it to a binding
or something but interpretation itself
is you know it's it's actually really
easy to do like you just have to iterate
over your ast or your code and execute
and do what it says so in fact the the
evaluation part relies on kind of the
language that your interpreters written
in it's kind of like in it's yeah ends
up running it in the in the host
language yeah so yeah exactly
so you have to host language which is
the language
new interpreters written in and you have
the guest language which is the language
that the input program is written in and
yes there's this that the bigger the
divide between the host and the guest
language is two more interpretation you
have to do said the more work you have
to do for example you mentioned Python
let's say in Python you have list
comprehensions right it's a really
really concise way of you know that in
let's say generating lists right you can
say give me from all of these numbers
only the ones that are uneven add them
to this list and then give me the sum of
this list or something now let's say you
write an interpreter for Python list
comprehensions but you write it in C all
right and now you realize oh C does not
have a really nice to use data structure
called list so now so now you have to
write lists in C first in order you know
to be able to actually represent what
the user program is saying that you want
a list right and the greater this divide
between the guest and host language the
more you have to do if you go down even
further and you have you write your
interpreter in in assembly language for
example then you don't even have you
know a proper concept of I don't know
let's say the functions or something you
basically just jump around from
different labels to different labels
stuff like this right and then it gets
really hard because then you have the
let's say your guest you guest language
has a something called list
comprehension with I don't know what
else could there be like multi-threading
little dinners the fact is all of these
concepts that only exist in in in this
guest language which is you know on a
higher level of abstraction you could
say mm-hmm then they only exists there
and now you have to do real work to
translate them right and let's say the
divide is really small and you translate
you interpret Python in Ruby and Python
and Ruby share a lot of stuff both are
you know have object both have things
like list comprehension even they'll you
know they look different but you can
really it's easy to translate between
the two
then you just you know we go through
your code and you execute it as it says
and execute as it says in this case is
not a lot of work basically if we have
the statement like let X equal seven and
then and then print X where where do we
store this value of x in our evaluation
stage right somewhere in memory right
you need some kind of internal
representation that can hold this kind
of information that let's say your
language only consists of you know let
statements and numbers so you can say
let X equal seven and let I don't know a
equals ten or something then you need
some internal representation of numbers
and it could be really simple right it
could just be the numbers that the house
language has basically but if you
evaluate the program you you see okay
somebody wants to store something here
it the user wants to store seven under
the name X that we somewhere in the book
it's called an environment it's a data
structure it's basically let's say
hashmap right it's a mapping from name
to value and you need to store the value
and their name somewhere so that you can
later
if somebody says print X you can access
the number again and you know the more
advanced the values you want to store
are the more advanced your internal
representation has to get for example
numbers are you know basically existent
in in in every language that you might
want to use but let's say you have
something like no a struct or something
right the user says this is my struct it
has three fields and then it says let
person equals person struck with first
name foo last name bar age 25 or
something and then your host language
needs some you know present
representation of this struct it needs
to map to the guest language so you can
so you're able to represent this all you
need to do some internal translation to
another construct that only exists in
the host language so like if I said let
x equal and then
I have a function right yeah and so I
cuz your language has first-class
functions yeah I don't I don't know the
go does it I'm no go experience yeah go
go has 5 functions yeah okay
well let's pretend it doesn't so then
you need you're saying you need some way
to store in your hash map like some
representation of this yeah yeah and
then you exactly so this is a great
example because a function is not as
easily representable as a number so in
go for example you could represent a
monkey function by defining a struct
right and then you can see what what
what is a function really okay a
function is it has like arguments right
named arguments it has a b c d it takes
in as argument and it has a function
body and a function body is okay this is
just ast node it's a sequence of
statements that gets executed when you
call this function okay that's not oh
I'd like you define a struct and you say
my parameters are a list of identifiers
of names basically and a function has a
body and that is an ast node of program
statements for example and then if if
you say let x equals function ABCD with
the body puts ABCD that prints ABCD then
in your hair up in your environment you
save a representation of this function
is struck with these two fields filled
out and you save it under the name X and
then later if your program says yes
let's call the function X then you fetch
X the function from your environment and
then you call it which is a different
thing basically but this is how you
could represent functions yeah so you're
like you're actually storing parts of
the ast in some sort of wrapper in this
environment which is in fact a
dictionary that you're just carrying
around right yeah yeah and I mean this
is a this is a really really simplified
way of putting it like it's not the most
advanced of techniques right and there
again the lines get read a really blurry
because your question basically
as in this direction when you said thus
let's go have first-class functions like
because you what your question hint that
is that can we represent a construct
from the guest language in something
that's that the host language has right
if the yeah if the guest language has
numbers and the host language has
numbers yeah no no question about let's
just use numbers for you know if you
don't need anything more but if we need
to store like functions like then the
question is can a host language generate
functions at runtime right which is what
we would need to do when we interpret
stuff because remember we're not
compiling we actually you know
generating stuff at run time while we're
executing the or interpreting this this
program and then we need to represent
this can we use the host language for
this in Ruby for example you could you
could create objects or you know an
unction or method in Ruby is just an
object so you could create objects in
Ruby that represent your your guest
function and then you could call those
objects but you know in other languages
you do not have objects for examples
that you can create at runtime so you
need another data structure to represent
your guest data structure basically and
this gets really really interesting the
more you know advance your
implementation gets if you add
compilation to this if you add JIT
compilation to this then you get in like
the really interesting territory of how
to represent certain things and then you
realize in the end it's all about
representation right like yeah because
compilers have all the most advanced
compilers they have different
representations for the same piece of
program and these different
representations are different in you
know the amount of detail they contain
for example the first representation may
contain a lot of detail it contains you
know like syntactic stuff for example
comments basically right and then the
compiler can control compiler and say
this function needs a comment or
something but then the compiler takes
this representation and turns it into
another representation that does not
contain comments for example and it does
not contain user readable names for
example it doesn't contain in
foobar it only contains like name one or
something again an ID and internal thing
and then it turns this representation
into a really dense byte code and then
it turns this into machine code and then
it turns then it you know optimizes this
machine code because this machine code
is easy to optimize and then it actually
hits this machine code so it's like a
complicated language may may have like
many AST s like it creates an AST and
then it might yeah an optimized version
of that and then a more optimized
version and yeah like that the word is a
internal representation ir miss the
shortened form and an AST is just a
internal representation bytecode is
another form of internal representation
and the most advanced compilers they
have different stages of this internal
representation because different stages
can represent different details that are
only relevant for a certain stage of
compilation interesting so your language
you said it's like three thousand lines
of code including tests so do you know
what percentage of it falls into these
kind of three categories we've discussed
like lexing versus parsing versus
evaluating yeah I think I would say
let's leave the tests aside and just say
did the code the implementation code and
then I would say 20 percent is the lexer
then I would say I don't know 50 or 60
percent is the parser and then the rest
is evaluation because the parser is in
the first book it's the most complex
thing in the whole in the whole
interpreter basically interesting what
makes the parser to the most complex I
would say because it needs the the ast
as an internal representation so I
include this in you know the parcel you
could probably say you can divide that
in half and say ast it's like the the
definition of all the different nodes in
this abstract syntax tree takes up a lot
of space and then the part that takes up
a lot of space the more you add to a
language which means the more syntax you
add to a language longer your posit gets
basically so your language it's a real
language and it's like 3,000 lines so
are there other language
there with with similarly concise
interpreter implementations now that you
mention that guess one of the most
widely used languages that has really
small implementation might be Lua mmm
which I think at the time was like I'm
making stuff up I guess it but it was
like as twenty thousand lines of C code
or something or fifteen thousand lines
of C code which is which is not a lot
compared to you know a lot of other
languages so what's the what's the
biggest do you think I don't know the
GCC like that the the new compiler
collection this is what it's like five
million lines of code or something like
it's it's you wow it's huge and then I
would say the JVM for example is a beast
because it does all of this advanced
stuff that optimizations JIT compilation
and stuff like this and I guess you know
people always say that Scala is a really
complex language because it allows the
user to do a lot of different things
right so it needs to be you know if you
want to do a lot of different things you
need to do a lot of different things
that that means you know it takes up
more code basically C++ I guess is one
of the most complex languages out there
and the compiler is you know also
complex I guess but I don't know any you
know concrete numbers base again yeah
well it's interesting how these sizes
vary right from Lua out a couple yeah
yeah and I don't if you think about it
really depends on what the language is
able to do ranks and so that goes back
to your lowest a memory because Lua yeah
it's like a wrapper around C right so it
kind of yeah it exposes a lot of the
yeah it exposes a lot of the or you can
use a lot of this the lower level stuff
in the in the C standard library and
Lipsy basically or in you can use
syscalls which you know it's the things
or are the things that the current
provides but if you don't have this then
you you know you need to be able to
provide certain things in your language
so you can reuse them and if you have
enough tools in the in the base layers
of your language you can use these tools
to build other stuff on top but you need
to have a certain amount of tools in
your toolbox otherwise
you know that there's no way that you
can add anything so I think that like we
kind of covered what interpreter is and
kind of some of the stages of it and
some things about their size so I want
to ask you some more like high level
questions hmm what do I learn from from
writing an interpreter
why should I write one because it's fun
there's a bunch of other reasons but let
me just say that it really is fun
writing interpreter was basically the
most fun I ever had programming because
it's it's really nice that you can write
a program that does not depend on
anything else you're basically inventing
things in the air like you're saying
okay I have nothing right now but now
let's create a string in this fictional
language called monkey and now let's
create a program that takes in this
fictional monkey language and it outputs
hello world all right it you do not
depend on a database you do not depend
on an internet connection you do not
depend on a huge standard library you do
not depend on third-party libraries and
you do not depend on your operating
system all you depend on is basically
what's in front of you in the code and
it's it's really pleasant to work on
programming languages because of that
because you basically you're inventing
the thing that you want to work with
right it's it's I don't know it to me it
feels like playing with LEGOs basically
like you can can make stuff up but
that's that's a fun part right but the
more serious answer is that by
implementing an interpreter you learn
about parsing as I said like it's a it's
a huge part of the interpreter and once
you understand parsing you understand a
lot of other stuff that's happening all
around you when you're programming and
then you're able to create all sorts of
different solutions for different
problems let's say you know you need to
analyze some input that you get in your
web application right
maybe it's complicated and maybe you
can't handle it as it comes over the
wire and maybe you need it in another
representation then yeah you can use the
knowledge you gain by writing a parser
and write another parser that you know
parses the input basically yeah so I
haven't
example like after I read your book I
had to do something at work involving
rules for when a library has like a
potential security issues and the rules
that represented as like strings of
version numbers like less than greater
than yeah it could be like this library
is safe if the versions like less than 1
or greater than equal to 1.7 or you know
greater than 7 and and so on right yeah
yeah a bunch of ranges right it seems
simple but but in fact there's like a
order of operations problem because you
have a bunch of ands and ORS hmm yeah
and so immediately it clicked to me that
this is something that you've built in
your parser that you need to turn this
into a tree yeah yeah exactly like if
you didn't know about parses what you
probably would have done or what I would
have done is you bring out this this big
fat hammer called wreck X right and you
just try to bang away at it right and
you're a drag extend stuff I guess and
then you end up realizing no wait
there's a order to it and that means in
in parses world it means precedence
right so you're saying okay like the end
thing that you have in your rules it has
a higher precedence than for example the
greater than or less than so this needs
to be somehow respected right when I'm
building this up or then and then once
you have your rules you basically want
to you also
most probably want to say it is a valid
rule that means you need to interpret it
okay so you parse it and then you have
this internal representation of your
rule and then you need to make sure that
all the parts that you need are there
thus every sub component of this rule
have like a left and right hand side
like two versions does it have the less
than or the greater than symbol in the
middle or is there another symbol in the
middle and you can go a long way with
red X sure but you're most likely gonna
hurt yourself at a certain point and you
realize hey if I would have just known
how to write a part that this would have
been you know a lot easier and yeah
perfect example of how you can use this
knowledge and transfer it to to another
thing if people that they want to build
an interpreter like what what
programming language concept is out
there like that doesn't have
representation like what language should
be built do you have any ideas for like
a language feature
that that is interesting that doesn't
exist or oh you mean if you want to have
something unique or something in your
language yeah so like monkey has a
feature that a number of languages do
but not all of them right which is that
you can assign if statements to values
right like it's an expression oriented
right yeah yeah that's like not every
language has that but I think it's a
great feature right so are there other
features that you think that would be
interesting what I want to implement is
pattern matching all right that like
pattern matching is like a really
concise way of representing basically
conditionals right and it's really
interesting to implement which I don't
know yet how to do exactly but I've been
thinking about this for the last couple
of months basically but pattern matching
could be its own thing in your host
language so that you implement pattern
matching directly in the host language
or you could maybe translate your
patterns into just conditionals in your
guest language and then you interpret
those right just different things to it
then what's also super interesting is
concurrency if you add like a
concurrency model to your language
there's a bunch of different models out
there for example Erlang has like an
actor/model of concurrency go follows a
model called you know it go has go
routines basic which is something called
green thread which can talk to each
other through channels which would also
be interesting to implement then scheme
languages have the concept of
co-routines which are interesting which
allow you to and I'm sure I'm you know
saying something wrong here but which
allow you to basically stop execution or
resume execution of your program under
certain conditions which is quite an
interesting thing to wrap your head
around and you know in addition to that
there's all sorts of syntactic things
you can do with the language like what
do you allow your identifies to look at
do you allow special characters for
example like Ruby does so you can put a
question mark in your function name and
stuff like this and you know all sorts
of things and may
you add some some funky data structure
you know instead of just having hashes
and rays and strings and numbers you add
something else like the maybe the main
data structure in your program is a tree
data structure or something and there's
different languages where you know for
example I don't know let's say a sequel
is its its own programming language
right and everything like it's a
declarative programming language so it
has a really specific view of the world
it only has you know statements that
allow you to describe how you want to
fetch or manipulate data so it's totally
different than you know a
general-purpose language so maybe you
can write a language it goes in this
direction like really specific to a
certain use case like a DSL for example
it seems like a fun it seems like a fun
area to play in right like we work with
programming languages all day yeah yeah
yeah so a lot of my readers they wrote
to me and they said look here I took
your monkey language but I added this I
added modules I added concurrency I
added list comprehensions I added for
loops which I didn't include in the book
and somehow a lot of people want I added
I don't know a bunch of other stuff then
another reader just emailed me this
morning saying hey here I took the thing
from your book but turned it into a
basic interpreter but it's my version of
basic I combined all of the aspects of
basic that I like from different basic
implementations and make my own so
there's so much creativity in this and
if I look through github of all the
projects that people send me whether it
took the basic monkey interpreter and
then turned it into something completely
different it's just you know astounded
by the creativity it's it's really
amazing it's so much fun because as I
said like it's fun to work with because
to a certain extent you only constrained
by basically your knowledge of
programming constructs and your
creativity you know and you can add a
lot of stuff to your language that's not
you know that that's really easy to
implement but nobody ever thought about
it before but you can if you just you
know have the imagination for it well
that is like a really exciting thought
and I think it's a great place to
and things so yeah Thurston thank you so
much for coming on the show I really
enjoyed your book I recommend people
check it out where can listeners find
your book yeah you can find the book the
first one writing an interpreting go at
interpreter book calm and you can find
the second one the sequel at compiled a
book calm and the book itself is called
writing a compiler and go and you know
it's it's actually a real sequel so you
need to start with the first one to get
the second one because they build upon
each other but yes interpreter book calm
and compiler book calm thank you very
much Thurston this is adam gordon bell
for software engineering radio thank you
for listening digitalocean is the
easiest cloud platform to deploy manage
and scale applications of any size
removing infrastructure friction and
providing predictability so developers
and their teams can deploy faster and
focus on building software the customers
love with thousands of in-depth
tutorials and an active community we
provide the support you need
digitalocean stands out of the crowd due
to its simplicity and high performance
with no billing surprises try
digitalocean for free by getting a 100
dollar infrastructure credit at doco /sc
radio thanks for listening to se radio
an educational program brought to you by
Archer police software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our web site at SC dash
radio net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack channel at SC
radio.com
you can also email us at team @ SC -
radio net this and all other episodes of
se radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license 2.5 thanks for listening